<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Jetty WebServer</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <link REL="icon" HREF="./images/jicon.gif" TYPE="image/gif"/>
    <iframe src="http://www.webtide.com/include/inc_offers.jsp" class="offers">
       <a href="http://www.webtide.com">Webtide special offers</a>
    </iframe>
     <iframe src="http://www.webtide.com/include/inc_blog.jsp" class="study">
       <a href="http://blogs.webtide.com">Blogs about Jetty.</a>
    </iframe>

<div class="summary">
 <div class="news"></div>
<p>
<span>Jetty</span> is a HTTP server, HTTP client, and Servlet container with small
foot print, embeddability, enterprise scalability and advanced asynchronous features. 
</p>
<p>
First created in 1995, Jetty has benefitted from input from a vast user community and consistent and
focused development by a stable core of lead developers. On the 24th of March, 2009, the Jetty-7 code base 
was converted to org.eclipse.jetty package space and checked  into the Eclipse Jetty SVN repository.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.eclipse.org/jetty/">Jetty is now in incubation at the Eclipse Foundation</a>. 
Once established as an Eclipse project, it will be dual-licensed, maintaining its current Apache 2.0 <a href="./LICENSE.TXT">license</a>,
and adding the Eclipse Public License. Jetty may be used and distributed under the terms of either. It is free for commercial use and distribution.
</p>
<p>
<b>Full commercial support, training and development services for Jetty
and Jetty-based projects are available from <a href="http://www.webtide.com/">Webtide</a>.
</b>
</p>

<h1>Jetty can be used as</h1>
<ul>
  <li>a stand-alone traditional web server for static and dynamic content</li>
  <li>a dynamic content server behind a dedicated HTTP server such as Apache using mod_proxy</li>
  <li>an embedded component within a Java application</li>
</ul>

<h1>Jetty is</h1>
<div class="feature">
<h2>Simple</h2>
We want to make Jetty easy to understand and use: 
<ul>
  <li>Configurable using either API or XML</li>
  <li>XML file syntax is a straightforward mapping from the API operating on POJOs</li>
  <li>Minimal number of lines required to embed a Jetty instance</li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="feature">
<h2>Scalable</h2>
In asynchronous Web 2.0 type applications using techniques such as AJAX,
connections stay open longer than when serving static pages, and thread
and memory requirements can escalate drastically. With Jetty...
<ul>
  <li>Performance degrades gracefully under stress for high quality of service</li>
  <li>Handle large user loads and long-lived sessions with <a href="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/JETTY/Continuations">continuations</a>, while working within the framework of existing web specifications</li>
  <li>Integrate with available clustering options such as <a href="http://wadi.codehaus.org">WADI</a> and <a href="http://www.terracotta.org">Terracotta</a></li>
</ul>
</div>

<div class="feature">
<h2>Efficient</h2>
A lot of effort goes into optimizing Jetty's performance and crafting the code so as to make the footprint as small as possible:
<ul>
<li>The core is kept small; extra functionality is in optional jars and dependencies are kept to a minimum</li>
<li>Scalability is a key concern</li>
<li>Performance degrades gracefully under stress</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="feature">
<h2>Embeddable</h2>
Jetty is designed to be a good component:
  <ul>
    <li>Usage of dependency injection and inversion of control patterns</li>
  </ul>
</div>
<div class="feature">
<h2>Pluggable</h2>
Jetty is architected for pluggability:
  <ul>
    <li>Use a provided implementation</li>
    <li>Code your own using the provided interfaces and abstract classes</li>
  </ul>
</div>

<h1>Jetty can be seen</h1>
 <ul>
  <li>shipped with products to provide out-of-the-box usability eg  <a href="http://tapestry.sourceforge.net">Tapestry</a>, <a href="http://www.liferay.com/">Liferay</a></li>
  <li>distributed on CDs with books to make examples and exercises ready-to-run</li>
  <li>incorporated into applications as a HTTP transport eg <a href="http://www.jxta.org/">JXTA</a>, <a href="http://www.mx4j.org">MX4J</a></li>
  <li>integrated as a web container in JavaEE app servers eg <a href="http://www.objectweb.org/jonas/index.html">JOnAS</a>, <a href="http://geronimo.apache.org">Geronimo</a>, <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/jboss//">JBoss</a>, <a href="http://www.huihoo.org/jfox">JFox</a></li>
  <li>included as a component of an application eg <a href="http://maven.apache.org/continuum">Continuum</a>, <a href="http://www.cenqua.com/fisheye">FishEye</a>, <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</a></li>
 </ul>

<p>
The <a href="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/JETTY/Jetty+Powered">Jetty Powered Page</a> 
contains more examples from among the tens of thousands of production Jetty instances. Countless more websites and
products are based around Jetty, but because Jetty aims to be as unobtrusive as possible, Jetty is invisible!
</p>
</div>

<script src="http://www.google-analytics.com/urchin.js" type="text/javascript"></script>
<script type="text/javascript">_uacct="UA-1149868-3"; urchinTracker();</script>
  </body>
</document>
